/*L practica pero al final cuando haya una hoja*/
EXPERIENCIA
Lprac-Cuando algo de hacer el dibujito
Lprac-El cursor tiene que poder quedarse un enter abajo osea nomas la rayita abajo | y no deben haber ni espacios de mas y esas cosas.
Lprac-Cuando digan que la entrada cuenta "letras" hay que tener en cuenta eso de que hay à y hay ñ y cosas asi por lo que toca es mejor con los index en codepoint.//LETTERFRECUENCY 
Lprac-Divisiones por 0 CEEEROOO NOOO, CUIDADO
Lprac-math los senos y los cosenos estan en radianes,
Lprac-Cosas para mejorar eficiencia: se puede quitar el for si no se necesita, se puede quitar el stringtokenizer, que el readln devuelva de una el readline

/////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////
*P-la plantilla seria copiarla con el archivo, y luego cambiarle el nombre junto con las pruebas//buscar lo  de como definir las plantillas en eclpse//es complicado.

*P-utilizar un archivo para degugear, con algun nombre y q se pueda abrir facil-> mirar con eclipse//hacer el archivo en eclipse  y añadir la probrada a la plantilla.//nombre de la clase sin java

Lprac-mandar la salida a un archivo para ver esactamente como sale el archivo//caso exremo, y si no java > archivo salida

  *O-en el coding online no se aceptan funciones built-in o packages.
*O-Muchas veces se necesita un enter o un enter de mas da un wrong answer
*O-La clase se debe llamar Main

/////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////
* O-no mandarlo por mail, se introducen cosas etc.
   :algunas paginas en pag 16
 􀂎 Valladolid OJ (http://acm.uva.es/p)
􀂎 Ural OJ (http://acm.timus.ru)
􀂎 Saratov OJ (http://acm.sgu.ru)
 􀂎 ZJU OJ (http://acm.zju.edu.cn)
 􀂎 Official ACM Live Archive (http://cii-judge.baylor.edu/)
􀂎 Peking University Online Judge (http://acm.pku.edu.cn/JudgeOnline/)
 􀂎 Programming Challenges (http://www.programming-challenges.com)
//////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////

O-problemas con las cosas del rank, pss tonces mejor empezar con un alias raro, o incluso solo tenerlo para practicar y que no lo relacionen conmigo, con q sepan que soy bueno en las competencias es suficiente cierto??--> si es mejor, los mantengo alejados de mi y cuando quiera los puedo unir decir q son mios.
 *P-resolver los ADHOC para volver a la practica con el lenguaje.

*P-primero coding y solving problemas faciles, luego leo un libro de algoritms.
    : leo los algoritmos uno a uno, los entiendo y los hago en el lenguaje.
*Lprac-si no es exponencial se manda, por experiencia se dice q si toma mas de 10 seg es exponencial y no se manda.
*Lprac-tener en cuenta el limite de algo iterando sobre un millon o algo iterando sobre la mitad de 10^5//La tablita de este man.
*Lprac-partir las llamadas a funciones es mejor asi porque desde el debugger se hace mas facil saber cual fue la salida de la funcion.
Lprac-utilizar temps, y if else completos para simplificar codigo, y poder ver en el debug.
*Lprac-naming
   :leer lo de hungarian y lo de poner los tipos de las variables junto con los nombres.
   :usar iI,iK,iM en ves de i j k  por los copy paste.
 PLAN DE ATAQUE :
*Knowledge of standard algorithms and the ability to find an appropriate algorithm 
*for every problem in the set;  
*Ž  Ability to code an algorithm into a working program; and  
*Ž  Having a strategy of cooperation with your teammates. 

*P-tipos: ya lo he visto, no lo he visto, lo he resuelto
  : pagina 18 los tipos de problemas.

*Lprac-complejidad, son n! permutacion y 2^n combinaciones, para un n^3 la entrada es como 39 de n es suficiente nlog n, toca ver con los nuevos problemas.
*Lprac-las entradas de sampel son muy triviales, por lo que las pruebas con estos no son suficientes. 

*P1. Proof of algorithm correctness (especially for Greedy algorithms) 
*P2. Time/Space complexity analysis for non recursive algorithms. 
*P 3. For recursive algorithms, the knowledge of computing recurrence relations and analyze 
them: iterative method, substitution method, recursion tree method and finally, Master 
Theorem 
*P4. Analysis of randomized algorithm which involves probabilistic knowledge, e.g: Random 
 variable, Expectation, etc.  
*P5. Amortized analysis.  
*P6. Output-sensitive analysis, to analyze algorithm which depends on output size, example: 
O(n log k) LIS algorithm, which depends on k,

LpracPRUEBAS

*P Some team coaches sometime ask their students to compete with each other by designing 
test cases. If student A's test cases can break other student's code, then A will get bonus 
point. You may want to try this in your school team training too. 

*Lprac1. Must include sample input, the most trivial one, you even have the answer given. 
Lprac2. Must include boundary cases, what is the maximum n,x,y, or other input variables, try 
varying their values to test for out of bound errors. 
*Lprac 3. For multiple input test case, try using two identical test case consecutively. Both must 
output the same result. This is to check whether you forgot to initialize some variables, 
which will be easily identified if the first instance produce correct output but the second 
 one doesn't. 
*Lprac4. Increase the size of input. Sometimes your program works for small input size, but 
behave wrongly when input size increases.  
*Lprac5. Tricky test cases, analyze the problem description and identify parts that are tricky, test 
 them to your code. 
*Lprac6. Don't assume input will always nicely formatted if the problem description didn't say  
so. Try inserting white spaces (space, tabs) in your input, check whether your code is able 
 to read in the values correctly 
*Lprac7. Finally, do random test cases, try random input and check your code's correctness. 

*LpracPLAN DE ATAQUE

*Lprac1. Order the problems: shortest job first, in terms of your effort (shortest to longest: 
 done it before, easy, unfamiliar, hard). 
*Lprac2. Sketch the algorithms, complexity, the numbers, data structures, tricky details. 
*Lprac3. Brainstorm other possible algorithms (if any) - then pick the stupidest that works! 
*Lprac 4. Do the Math! (space & time complexity & plug-in actual expected & worst case 
numbers). 
*Lprac5. Code it of course, as fast as possible, and it must be correct. 
*Lprac6. Try to break the algorithm - use special (degenerate?) test cases. 

*LpracCODING 
*Lprac Only coding after you finalize your algorithm. 
*Lprac2. Create test data for tricky cases. 
*Lprac3. Code the input routine and test it (write extra output routines to show data). 
*Lprac4. Code the output routine and test it. 
*Lprac 5. Write data structures needed. 
*Lprac6. Stepwise refinement: write comments outlining the program logic. 
*Lprac7. Fill in code and debug one section at a time. 
*Lprac8. Get it working & verify correctness (use trivial test cases). 
*Lprac 9. Try to break the code - use special cases for code correctness. 

*LpracCONTINGENCIA

*Lprac How long have you spent debugging it already?  
*Lprac2. What type of bug do you seem to have?  
*Lprac3. Is your algorithm wrong?  
*Lprac 4. Do you data structures need to be changed?  
*Lprac5. Do you have any clue about what's going wrong?  
*Lprac6. A short amount (20 mins) of debugging is better than switching to anything else; 
but you might be able to solve another from scratch in 45 mins.  
*Lprac 7. When do you go back to a problem you've abandoned previously?  
*Lprac8. When do you spend more time optimizing a program, and when do you switch?  
*Lprac9. Consider from here out - forget prior effort, focus on the future: how can you get 
*Lprac the most points in the next hour with what you have? 

*LpracTRICKS

*Lprac3. Hint: focus on limits (specified in problem statement). 
*Lprac4. Waste memory when it makes your life easier (trade memory space for speed). 
*Lprac 5. Don't delete your extra debugging output, comment it out. 
*Lprac6. Optimize progressively, and only as much as needed. 
*Lprac7. Keep all working versions! 
*Lprac8. Code to debug: 
*Lpraca. white space is good, 
*Lpracb. use meaningful variable names, //gregorian
*Lprac c. don't reuse variables, (we are not doing software engineering here) 
*Lpracd. stepwise refinement, 
*Lprace. Comment before code. 
*Lprac9. Avoid pointers if you can. 
*Lprac10. Avoid dynamic memory like the plague: statically allocate everything. (yeah 
 yeah) 
*Lprac11. Try not to use floating point; if you have to, put tolerances in everywhere (never 
test equality) 
*Lprac12. Comments on comments: 
*Lpraca. Not long prose, just brief notes. 
*Lpracb. Explain high-level functionality: ++i; /* increase the value of i by */ is 
 worse than useless. 
*Lpracc. Explain code trickery. 
*Lpracd. Delimit & document functional sections

*Lpracestructuras de datos

*LpracWill it work?
*Lpractener en cuenta las preguntas q se le van a hacer a las estructuras, y o agregar mas info o cambiar

*LpracCan I code it? 
*Lpracme acuerdo?, cabe en la memoria todo?

*LpracCan I code it in time? or has my programming language support it yet?

*LpracCan I debug it? 
*Lpracel estado, la impresion de arboles y de listas.

*Lprac it is fast?
*Lpracalgunos reducen la complejidad de un algoritmo

*LpracEVITAR
*Lprac-ponerle cuidado a los null pointer
*Lprac-coolnes

*LpracTIPOS DE DATOS

*Lpracarray: insertar ordenado es lento, borrar tambien, lo de aumentar el tamaño.

*Lpraclinked list: insertar ordenado tiene que buscar desde el principio, es como un array solo que su insersion es mas rapida y borrado tambien.

*Lpracstack(pila):
*Lprac--1. To model "real stack" in computer world: Recursion, Procedure Calling, etc. 
*Lprac2. Checking palindrome (although checking palindrome using Queue & Stack is 'stupid'). 
*Lprac3. To read an input from keyboard in text editing with backspace key.  
*Lprac 4. To reverse input data, (another stupid idea to use stack for reversing data). 
*Lprac5. Checking balanced parentheses. 
*Lprac6. Postfix calculation. 
*Lprac7. Converting mathematical expressions. Prefix, Infix, or Postfix.

*LpracQueue(cola):

*LpracINPUT
*Lpracmanejar perfectamente la lectura de entradas: practicar y desmenbrar scanner//ya no ahora es bufferreader.

*Lpractener en cuenta las inicializaciones, y los espacios en blanco y todo eso.

*LpracBRUTE FORCE METHOD

*Lpracdebe ser el primero en considerar, es "facil" de codificar y si da para el tiempo debe ser utilizado.

*LpracRECURSION

*Lpracmas facil de conceptualizar, o son mas rapidas.

*LpracExamples: Tower of Hanoi, Searching (DFS, BFS), etc. 

*LpracUno primero mira como resolver el caso base luego asume solucion para n-1 y busca como llevar el caso a el n-1, 

*Lprac1. How can you define the problem in term of a smaller problem of the same type? 
*Lprac2. How does each recursive call diminish the size of the problem? 
*Lprac 3. What instance of the problem can serve as the base case? 
*Lprac4. As the problem size diminishes, will you reach this base case? 

*LpracDivide and Conquer 
*Lprac1. Divide data into parts 
*Lprac2. Find sub-solutions for each of the parts recursively (usually) 
*Lprac 3. Construct the final answer for the original problem from the sub-solutions 


*LpracGenerating vs Filtering

*Lpracfiltters easy to code, genrator dificult, hay q hacer la matematica, si no puede filters, hago un gerardor
*Lprac filters=muchas posibles soluciones escogo una.

*LpracPre-Computation / Pre-Calculation 

*Lpraca veces es mejor generar una lista larga de numeros primos, para usarlos en todo el programa.

*LpracSymetrias
*Lpraccosas como distancias,

*Lpracforward vs backward 
*Lpracmas rapido a veces

*LpracCHAPTER 7    MATHEMATICS 

*LpracBase Number Conversion
*Lpracsiempre utilizar 10 como una base intermedia y sacar los metodos para utilizar los char que es la forma mas facil.

**LpracBig Mod (b^p)%m
**Lpracnumeros muy grandes, se toma la iniciativa de dividir para conquistar.

    static long bigMod(long b,long p,long m){
        long resultado=0;
        if(p==0)
            return 1;
        else if(p%2==0)
         {
            long parcial=bigMod(b, p/2, m)%m;
            return (parcial*parcial)%m;
        }
        else return ((b%m)*bigMod(b,p-1,m))%m;
    }


*LpracBig Integer
*Lpracmas rapido division suma y multiplicaciones y esas cosas

*LpracCarmichael Number
>=3 factores primos 561,1105,1729,2465,2821,6601,8911,10585,15841,29341,41041,46657,52633,62745,63973 mirar eso, al parecer con 4 no funciona,

Catalan Formula

Catalan(n) =
2n!
 ---------------
n! * n! * (n+1)

                    (2n+2) * (2n+1)
Catalan(n+1) =--------------- * Catalan(n)
                     (n+1) * (n+2)


 Counting Combinations - C(N,K) 

nr donde n es el número de cosas que puedes elegir, y eliges r de ellas
 (Se puede repetir, el orden importa) 

 donde n es el número de cosas que puedes elegir, y eliges r de ellas
 (No se puede repetir, el orden importa)


  N! 
---------- 
(N-K)!*K!

me salte las convinaciones 

Divisors and Divisibility 

f d is a divisor of n, then so is n/d, but d & n/d cannot both be greater than sqrt(n). 

Exponentiation

Enfoque de dividir y vencer
long square(long n) { return n*n; }
long fastexp(long base,long power) {
if (power == 0)
return 1;
else if (power%2 == 0)
return square(fastexp(base,power/2));
 else
return base * (fastexp(base,power-1));
 }

formula
#include <stdio.h>
#include <math.h>
void main() {
printf("%lf\n",exp(log(8.0)*1/3.0));
printf("%lf\n",pow(8.0,1/3.0));
}

Factorial

long FacIter(int n) {
 int i,result = 1;
for (i=0; i<n; i++) result *= i;
return result;
}

Fibonacci

Dinamico o(n)
int fib(int n) {
int a=1,b=1,i,c;
for (i=3; i<=n; i++) {
c = a+b;
a = b;
b = c;
 }
return a;
}

Propiedas de matris fib O(log n)
Divide_Conquer_Fib(n) {
i = h = 1;
j = k = 0;
while (n > 0) {
if (n%2 == 1) { // if n is odd
t = j*h;
j = i*h + j*k + t;
i = i*k + t;
 }
t = h*h;
h = 2*k*h + t;
k = k*k + t;
n = (int) n/2;
} return j;}

Greatest Common Divisor (GCD)
Euclid's Algorithm.
int GCD(int a,int b) {
while (b > 0) {
a = a % b;
 a ^= b; b ^= a; a ^= b; } return a;
 }

Lowest Common Multiple (LCM)
LCM (m,n) = (m * n) / GCD (m,n)
LCM (3,2) = (3 * 2) / GCD (3,2)
LCM (3,2) = 6 / 1
LCM (3,2) = 6
Application of LCM -> to find a synchronization time between two traffic light, if traffic
 light A display green color every 3 minutes and traffic light B display green color every 2

Mathematical Expressions
Infix expression grammar:
<infix> = <identifier> | <infix><operator><infix>
 <operator> = + | - | * | / <identifier> = a | b | .... | z
(1 + 2) => 3,

Prefix expression grammar:
<prefix> = <identifier> | <operator><prefix><prefix>
<operator> = + | - | * | / <identifier> = a | b | .... | z
 Prefix expression example: (+ 1 2) => (1 + 2) = 3,

Postfix expression grammar:
<postfix> = <identifier> | <postfix><postfix><operator>
<operator> = + | - | * | / <identifier> = a | b | .... | z
 Postfix expression example: (1 2 +) => (1 + 2) = 3
////////////////////////
Lo que dice en la hoja y las implementaciones de pasar de postfix prefix y eso entre ellos y a arboles y desde arboles
/////////////////////


Infix statement: ( ( 4 - ( 1 + 2 * ( 6 / 3 ) - 5 ) ) ). This is what the algorithm will do, look
carefully at the steps.
Expression Stack (bottom to top) Postfix expression
//////////////////////////////////////////
 hay que copiar la tabla para sacar el algortimo
/////////////////////////////////////////

Prime Factors
For negative integers, multiply by -1 to make it positive again.
For -1,0, and 1, no prime factor. (by definition...)
 standart
int is_prime(int n) {
 long lim = (int) sqrt(n);
 for (int i=2; i<=lim; i++) if (n%i == 0) return 0; 
return 1;
}
void main() {
int i,count=0;
for (i=1; i<10000; i++) count += is_prime(i);
printf("Total of %d primes\n",count);
}

 3. Restatement of sqrt.///probar si es mas rapido que el otro sqrt
int is_prime(int n) {
for (int i=2; i*i<=n; i++) if (n%i == 0) return 0;
return 1;
}

int is_prime(int n) {
if (n == 1) return 0; // 1 is NOT a prime
 if (n == 2) return 1; // 2 is a prime
if (n%2 == 0) return 0; // NO prime is EVEN, except 2
for (int i=3; i*i<=n; i+=2) // start from 3, jump 2 numbers
if (n%i == 0) // no need to check even numbers
return 0;
 return 1;
}

1. Create a large array. How large?
2. Suppose max primes generated will not greater than 2^31-1
(2,147,483,647), maximum 32-bit integer.
3. Since you need smaller primes below sqrt(N), you only need to
 store primes from 1 to sqrt(2^31)
4. Quick calculation will show that of sqrt(2^31) = 46340.95.
5. After some calculation, you'll find out that there will be at most 4792 primes in the
range 1 to 46340.95. So you only need about array of size (roughly) 4800 elements.
 6. Generate that prime numbers from 1 to 46340.955. This will take time, but when you
already have those 4792 primes in hand, you'll be able to use those values to determine
whether a bigger number is a prime or not.
 7. Now you have 4792 first primes in hand. All you have to do next is to check whether
a big number N a prime or not by dividing it with small primes up to sqrt(N). If you can
find at least one small primes can divide N, then N is not prime, otherwise N is prime.

pegar sieve

void sieve(int L,int U) {
int i,j,d;
d=U-L+1; /* from range L to U, we have d=U-L+1 numbers. */
/* use flag[i] to mark whether (L+i) is a prime number or not. */
bool *flag=new bool[d];
 for (i=0;i<d;i++) flag[i]=true; /* default: mark all to be true */
for (i=(L%2!=0);i<d;i+=2) flag[i]=false;
/* sieve by prime factors staring from 3 till sqrt(U) */
for (i=3;i<=sqrt(U);i+=2) {
if (i>L && !flag[i-L]) continue;
 /* choose the first number to be sieved -- >=L,
divisible by i, and not i itself! */
j=L/i*i; if (j<L) j+=i;
if (j==i) j+=i; /* if j is a prime number, have to start form next
one */
j-=L; /* change j to the index representing j */
 for (;j<d;j+=i) flag[j]=false;
}
if (L<=1) flag[1-L]=false;
if (L<=2) flag[2-L]=true;
for (i=0;i<d;i++) if (flag[i]) cout << (L+i) << " ";
cout << endl;
}

 SORTING
 stability
Bubble Sort

BubbleSort(A)
for i <- length[A]-1 down to 1
for j <- 0 to i-1
if (A[j] > A[j+1]) // change ">" to "<" to do a descending sort
temp <- A[j]
 A[j] <- A[j+1]
A[j+1] <- temp

tener en cuenta el bubble y que el swap se hace entre objetos adjacentes.

QuickSort(A,p,r) 
  if p < r 
    q <- Partition(A,p,r) 
    QuickSort(A,p,q) 
     QuickSort(A,q+1,r)

// Test.java para el comparator de quicksort en juava
import java.util.Comparator;

import java.util.PriorityQueue;


public class Test
{

    public static void main(String[] args)

    {
        Comparator<String> comparator = new StringLengthComparator

        PriorityQueue<String> queue = 

            new PriorityQueue<String>(10, comparator);

        queue.add("short");
        queue.add("very long indeed");

        queue.add("medium");
        while (queue.size() != 0)


        {
            System.out.println(queue.remove());

        }
    }
}

// StringLengthComparator.java

import java.util.Comparator;


public class StringLengthComparator implements Comparator<String>

{
    @Override
    public int compare(String x, String y)

    {
        // Assume neither string is null. Real code should
        // probably be more robust

        if (x.length() < y.length())


        {
            return -1;

        }
        if (x.length() > y.length())


        {
            return 1;
        }

        return 0;
    }
}

Multi field sorting, advanced sorting technique 

The better way to do multi field sorting is to modify the compare_function in such a way 
that you break ties accordingly

typedef struct { 
   int day,month,year; 
  char *name; 
} birthday; 
int compare_function(const void *a,const void *b) { 
  birthday *x = (birthday *) a; 
  birthday *y = (birthday *) b; 
  if (x->month != y->month) // months different 
     return x->month - y->month; // sort by month 
else { // months equal..., try the 2nd field... day 
    if (x->day != y->day) // days different 
      return x->day - y->day; // sort by day 
     else // days equal, try the 3rd field... year 
      return x->year - y->year; // sort by year 
  } 
}

b. Counting Sort 
For Counting Sort, we assume that the numbers are in the range [0..k], where k is at most 
 O(n). We set up a counter array which counts how many duplicates inside the input, and 
the reorder the output accordingly, without any comparison at all. Complexity is O(n+k). 
c. Radix Sort 
For Radix Sort, we assume that the input are n d-digits number, where d is reasonably 
 limited. 
Radix Sort will then sorts these number digit by digit, starting with the least significant 
digit to the most significant digit. It usually use a stable sort algorithm to sort the digits, 
such as Counting Sort above. 

SEARCHING

function binarySearch(a, value, left, right) 
    if right < left 
        return not found 
    mid := floor((left+right)/2) 
    if a[mid] = value 
        return mid 
    if value < a[mid] 
         binarySearch(a, value, left, mid-1) 
    else 
        binarySearch(a, value, mid+1, right) 

Arboles binarios
der>raiz>izq tienen que ser balanceados, rojinegros//buscar todas las clases de esto en java, treeset 

Diccionarios// hashset
son hash tables, manejo de colisiones

Hash Table variations 
It is often quite useful to store more information that just the value. One example is when 
searching a small subset of a large subset, and using the hash table to store locations 
 visited, you may want the value for searching a location in the hash table with it. 

CHAPTER 10 GREEDY ALGORITHMS

Greedy algorithms are algorithms which follow the problem solving meta-heuristic of
making the locally optimum choice at each stage with the hope of finding the global
 optimum.
"At each stage visit the nearest unvisited city to the current city"

-If a greedy algorithm can be proven to yield the global optimum for a given problem
class, it typically becomes the method of choice.

In general, greedy algorithms have five pillars:
♦ A candidate set, from which a solution is created
♦ A selection function, which chooses the best candidate to be added to the solution
♦ A feasibility function, that is used to determine if a candidate can be used to contribute to a solution
 ♦ An objective function, which assigns a value to a solution, or a partial solution, and
♦ A solution function, which will indicate when we have discovered a complete solution

- The real challenge for the programmer lies in the fact that greedy solutions don't always work
 -so at each step, there is always an optimal answer which is a superset of the current state. Thus, the final answer is optimal.
-If the greedy algorithm finds the correct answer, go for it, but don't get suckered into thinking the greedy solution will work for all problems.

/*traducir a algoritmo
Topological Sort
Given a collection of objects, along with some ordering constraints, such as "A must be
before B," find an order of the objects such that all the ordering constraints hold.
 Algorithm: Create a directed graph over the objects, where there is an arc from A to B if
"A must be before B." Make a pass through the objects in arbitrary order. Each time you
find an object with in-degree of 0, greedily place it on the end of the current ordering,
 delete all of its out-arcs, and recurse on its (former) children, performing the same check.
If this algorithm gets through all the objects without putting every object in the ordering,
there is no ordering which satisfies the constraints.*/

DYNAMIC PROGRAMMING 

problem must have: 
1. Optimal sub-structure property: 
    Optimal solution to the problem contains within it optimal solutions to sub-problems 
2. Overlapping sub-problems property 
     We accidentally recalculate the same problem twice or more.

Fibonacci
#include <stdio.h> 
#define MAX 20 // to test with bigger number, adjust this value 
int memo[MAX]; // array to store the previous calculations 
 // the slowest, unnecessary computation is repeated 
int Non_DP(int n) { 
  if (n==1 || n==2) 
    return 1;
else 
    return Non_DP(n-1) + Non_DP(n-2); 
} 
// top down DP 
int DP_Top_Down(int n) { 
   // base case 
  if (n == 1 || n == 2) 
    return 1; 
  // immediately return the previously computed result 
  if (memo[n] != 0) 
    return memo[n]; 
  // otherwise, do the same as Non_DP 
  memo[n] = DP_Top_Down(n-1) + DP_Top_Down(n-2); 
   return memo[n]; 
} 
// fastest DP, bottom up, store the previous results in array 
int DP_Bottom_Up(int n) { 
  memo[1] = memo[2] = 1; // default values for DP algorithm 
  // from 3 to n (we already know that fib(1) and fib(2) = 1 
   for (int i=3; i<=n; i++) 
    memo[i] = memo[i-1] + memo[i-2]; 
  return memo[n]; 
} 
void main() { 
  int z; 
  // this will be the slowest 
  for (z=1; z<MAX; z++) printf("%d-",Non_DP(z)); 
   printf("\n\n"); 
  // this will be much faster than the first 
  for (z=0; z<MAX; z++) memo[z] = 0; 
  for (z=1; z<MAX; z++) printf("%d-",DP_Top_Down(z)); 
  printf("\n\n"); 
   /* this normally will be the fastest */ 
  for (z=0; z<MAX; z++) memo[z] = 0; 
  for (z=1; z<MAX; z++) printf("%d-",DP_Bottom_Up(z)); 
  printf("\n\n"); 
} 

Matrix Chain Multiplication (MCM) 

Matrix-Multiply(A,B): 
  if columns[A] != columns[B] then 
    error "incompatible dimensions" 
  else 
    for i = 1 to rows[A] do 
      for j = 1 to columns[B] do 
        C[i,j]=0 
         for k = 1 to columns[A] do 
           C[i,j] = C[i,j] + A[i,k] * B[k,j] 
  return C


Matrix Chain Multiplication Problem

Step 1: characterize the optimal sub-structure of this problem. 
Let Ai..j (i < j) denote the result of multiplying AiAi+1..Aj. 
 Ai..j can be obtained by splitting it into Ai..k and Ak+1..j and then multiplying the sub-
products. There are j-i possible splits (i.e. k=i,...,j-1) 
Within the optimal parenthesization of Ai..j : 
(a) the parenthesization of Ai..k must be optimal 
 (b) the parenthesization of Ak+1..j must be optimal 

Step 2: Recursive formulation 
Need to find A1..n 
Let m[i,j] = minimum number of scalar multiplications needed to compute Ai..j 
Since Ai..j can be obtained by breaking it into Ai..k Ak+1..j, we have 
  
Step 3 Computing the Optimal Costs 
Matric-Chain-Order(p) 
  n = length[p]-1 
m[i,j] = 0, if i=j 
        = min i<=k<j { m[i,k]+m[k+1,j]+pi-1pkpj }, if i<j 
let s[i,j] be the value k where the optimal split occurs. 

for i = 1 to n do 
    m[i,i] = 0 
  for l = 2 to n do 
    for i = 1 to n-l+1 do 
      j = i+l-1 
      m[i,j] = infinity 
      for k = i to j-1 do 
        q = m[i,k] + m[k+1,j] + pi-1*pk*pj 
         if q < m[i,j] then 
          m[i,j] = q 
          s[i,j] = k 
  return m and s 
Step 4: Constructing an Optimal Solution 
Print-MCM(s,i,j) 
  if i=j then 
    print Ai 
  else 
    print "(" + Print-MCM(s,1,s[i,j]) + "*" + Print-MCM(s,s[i,j]+1,j) + 
 ")"

Longest Common Subsequence (LCS) 
 
A sequence Z is called common subsequence of sequence X and Y if Z is subsequence 
of both X and Y. X=<B,C,A,D> and Z=<C,A>. 

A sequence Z is called common subsequence of sequence X and Y if Z is subsequence 
 of both X and Y.

#include <stdio.h> 
#include <string.h> 
#define MAX 100 
 
char X[MAX],Y[MAX]; 
int i,j,m,n,c[MAX][MAX],b[MAX][MAX]; 
 
int LCSlength() { 
 
  m=strlen(X); 
   n=strlen(Y); 
 
  for (i=1;i<=m;i++) c[i][0]=0; 
  for (j=0;j<=n;j++) c[0][j]=0; 
 
  for (i=1;i<=m;i++) 
    for (j=1;j<=n;j++) { 
      if (X[i-1]==Y[j-1]) { 
        c[i][j]=c[i-1][j-1]+1; 
         b[i][j]=1; /* from north west */ 
      } 
 
      else if (c[i-1][j]>=c[i][j-1]) { 
      c[i][j]=c[i-1][j]; 
       b[i][j]=2; /* from north */ 
      } 
      else { 
        c[i][j]=c[i][j-1]; 
         b[i][j]=3; /* from west */ 
      }  
    } 
  return c[m][n]; 
}

void printLCS(int i,int j) { 
  if (i==0 || j==0) return; 
 
  if (b[i][j]==1) { 
    printLCS(i-1,j-1); 
   printf("%c",X[i-1]);} 
   else if (b[i][j]==2) 
    printLCS(i-1,j); 
  else 
    printLCS(i,j-1); 
} 
void main() { 
  while (1) { 
    gets(X); 
    if (feof(stdin)) break; /* press ctrl+z to terminate */ 
    gets(Y); 
     printf("LCS length -> %d\n",LCSlength()); /* count length */ 
    printLCS(m,n); /* reconstruct LCS */ 
    printf("\n"); 
  } 
}

Edit Distance 

Input: Given two string, Cost for deletion, insertion, and replace 
 Output: Give the minimum actions needed to transform first string into the second one.
A two-dimensional matrix, m[0..|s1|,0..|s2|] is used to hold the edit distance values, such 
that m[i,j] = d(s1[1..i], s2[1..j]). 
 m[0][0] = 0; 
for (i=1; i<length(s1); i++) m[i][0] = i; 
for (j=1; j<length(s2); j++) m[0][j] = j; 
for (i=0; i<length(s1); i++) 
  for (j=0; j<length(s2); j++) { 
    val = (s1[i] == s2[j]) ? 0 : 1; 
     m[i][j] = min( m[i-1][j-1] + val, 
                   min(m[i-1][j]+1 , m[i][j-1]+1)); 
  }

Longest Inc/Dec-reasing Subsequence (LIS/LDS) 
Input: Given a sequence 
Output: The longest subsequence of the given sequence such that all values in this 
 longest  subsequence is strictly increasing/decreasing.

for i = 1 to total-1 
  for j = i+1 to total 
    if height[j] > height[i] then 
      if length[i] + 1 > length[j] then 
        length[j] = length[i] + 1 
         predecessor[j] = i

There exist an O(n log k) algorithm to compute LIS (for LDS, this is just a reversed-LIS), 
where k is the size of the actual LIS.

0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8 
a    -7,10, 9, 2, 3, 8, 8, 1 
 A -i  i, i, i, i, i, i, i, i (iteration number, i = infinity) 
A -i -7, i, i, i, i, i, i, i (1) 
A -i -7,10, i, i, i, i, i, i (2) 
A -i -7, 9, i, i, i, i, i, i (3) 
A -i -7, 2, i, i, i, i, i, i (4) 
A -i -7, 2, 3, i, i, i, i, i (5) 
 A -i -7, 2, 3, 8, i, i, i, i (6) 
A -i -7, 2, 3, 8, i, i, i, i (7) 
A -i -7, 1, 3, 8, i, i, i, i (8)

HACERLO, DEL PROBLEMAS 481 - What Goes Up - need O(n log k) LIS

Zero-One Knapsack //falta lo de saber si sacar uno y meter el otro
 Input: N items, each with various Vi (Value) and Wi (Weight) and max Knapsack size 
 MW. 
Output: Maximum value of items that one can carry, if he can either take or not-take a 
particular item. 
Let C[i][w] be the maximum value if the available items are {X1,X2,...,Xi} and the 
knapsack size is w. 
 Ž  if i == 0 or w == 0 (if no item or knapsack full), we can't take anything C[i][w] = 0 
Ž  if Wi > w (this item too heavy for our knapsack),skip this item C[i][w] = C[i-1][w]; 
Ž  if Wi <= w, take the maximum of "not-take" or "take" C[i][w] = max(C[i-1][w] , 
 C[i-1][w-Wi]+Vi); 
Ž  The solution can be found in C[N][W]; 
for (i=0;i<=N ;i++) C[i][0] = 0; 
for (w=0;w<=MW;w++) C[0][w] = 0; 
 
for (i=1;i<=N;i++) 
  for (w=1;w<=MW;w++) { 
    if (Wi[i] > w) 
       C[i][w] = C[i-1][w]; 
    else 
      C[i][w] = max(C[i-1][w] , C[i-1][w-Wi[i]]+Vi[i]); 
  } 
output(C[N][MW]); 

Counting Change 
Input: A list of denominations and a value N  to be changed with these denominations 
 Output: Number of ways to change N 

#include <stdio.h> 
#define MAXTOTAL 10000 
long long nway[MAXTOTAL+1]; 
int coin[5] = { 50,25,10,5,1 }; 
 
void main()  
{ 
  int i,j,n,v,c; 
  scanf("%d",&n); 
   v = 5; 
  nway[0] = 1; 
  for (i=0; i<v; i++) { 
    c = coin[i]; 
    for (j=c; j<=n; j++) 
      nway[j] += nway[j-c]; 
  } 
  printf("%lld\n",nway[n]); 
} 

Maximum Interval Sum 
 Input: A sequence of integers 
Output: A sum of an interval starting from index i to index j (consecutive), this sum must 
be maximum among all possible sums. 
Numbers : -1 6 
Sum     : -1 6 
             ^ 
           max sum 
Numbers : 4 -5  4 -3  4  4 -4  4 -5 
Sum     : 4 -1  4  1  5  9  5  9  4 
             ^                 ^ 
            stop            max sum 
Numbers : -2 -3 -4 
Sum     : -2 -3 -4 
            ^ 
        max sum, but negative... (this is the maximum anyway) 
So, just do a linear sweep from left to right, accumulate the sum one element by one 
element, start new interval whenever you encounter partial sum < 0 (and record current 
 best maximum interval encountered so far)... 
At the end, output the value of the maximum intervals. 


TEST YOUR DP KNOWLEDGE 
Solve UVa problems related with Ad-Hoc DP: 
108 - Maximum Sum 
836 - Largest Submatrix 
 10003 - Cutting Sticks 
10465 - Homer Simpson

GRAPHS
Vertices and Edges
V = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6} 
E = {(1,3), (1,6), (2,5), (3,4), (3,6)}

Such vertices are termed ``isolated''.

- are called edge-weighted graphs (or weighted graphs)

- self-loop if it is of the form (u,u). The sample graph contains no self-loops. 

-multigraph=(lops y dobles edges) es dif a simplegraf

-(u,v) is  incident to both vertex 

-degree of a vertex is the number of edges which are incident to it

-directed, in which case the edges have a direction. In this case, the edges are called arcs. 
 -out-degree of a vertex is the number of arcs which begin at that vertex. The  in-degree blabla
-A path from vertex u to vertex x is a sequence of 
vertices (v 0, v 1, ..., v k) such that v 0 = u and v 
k = x and (v 0, v 1) is an edge in the graph, as is 
 (v 1, v 2), (v 2, v 3), etc. The length of such a 
path is k.

Graph Representation
-The vertices are generally tracked by numbering them, so that one can index them just by 
their number.



84

COSAS DE VELOCIDAD



Row major, cache-friendly, use this method to access all items in array sequentially. 
 for (i=0; i<numRow; i++)    // ROW FIRST = EFFECTIVE 
    for (j=0; j<numCol; j++) 
       array[i][j] = 0; 
 Column major, NOT cache-friendly, DO NOT use this method or you'll get very poor 
 performance. Why? you will learn this in Computer Architecture course. For now, just 
 take note that computer access array data in row major. 
 for (j=0; j<numCol; j++)    // COLUMN FIRST = INEFFECTIVE 
    for (i=0; i<numRow; i++) 
       array[i][j] = 0;



********************************************************
cosas de java:

No olvidarse de sort y de esas cosas pero tambien existe treemap que los mantiene ordenados
********************************************************

Arrays asist y esas cosas solo funcionan con Object como Integer o como int [] y no con tipos basicos como int
 **************************
int 2^32  2 147 483 648, long 2^63 = 9.22337204 × 10^18	

i.e. 1.98999 would round to 1.99
double roundTwoDecimals(double d) {
           DecimalFormat twoDForm = new DecimalFormat("#.##");
        return Double.valueOf(twoDForm.format(d));
}

la clase arrays, la clase collections, decimalformat aprender lo de la redondeada.


BREAK ETI;
 void gotoBreak() {
 System.out.println("Ejemplo de break como 'goto' ");
a: for( int i=1; i<10; i++ ){
System.out.print(" i="+i);
for( int j=1; j<10; j++ ){
if ( j==5 )
break a; //Sale de los dos bucles!!!
 System.out.print(" j="+j);
}
System.out.print("No llega aquí");
}
}

-------------
{
char b='B';
 System.out.println((int)b);//A=65, B=66 hasta Z
}

---------------------
En los comparables solo preocuparse por decir si soy mayor o menor, en vez de que necesite lo contrario


-- 
Oscar Chamat Caicedo
 Estudiante Ing. de Sistemas Univalle